[{"question":"The living organisms can be unexceptionally distinguished from the non-living things on the basis of their ability for:","a":"interaction with the environment and progressive evolution","b":"reproduction","c":"growth and movement","d":"responsiveness to touch","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which type of organisation is found in only living beings?","a":"Atomic","b":"Molecular","c":"Mixture ","d":"Sub-cellular","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Organisation levels in living beings are:","a":"Subcellular -› cellular -› individual -› community -› population","b":"Atomic -> molecular -› subcellular -> cellular -> tissue -> organ -> individual","c":"Individual -› population -› organ system › tissue -› cellular -› molecular -› atomic","d":"Atomic - › molecular - › tissue - › individual > ecosystem - › community.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"ICVCN is an abbrevited form of:","a":"International Code of Virus Nomenclature","b":"International Code for Virulence Nomenclature","c":"International Code of Viral Classification and Nomenclature","d":"International Code of Valuation in Nomenclature","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Taxonomic hierarchy refers to:","a":"step-wise arrangement of all categories for classification of plants and animals.","b":" A group of senior taxonomists who decide the nomenclature of plants and animals.","c":"a list of botanists or zoologists who have worked on taxonomy of a species or group.","d":"classification of a species, based on fossil record.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":" Growth, development and functioning of living body is due to:","a":"Order","b":"Homeostasis","c":"Metabolism","d":"Adaptation","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"System of classification used by Linnaeus was:","a":"Natural system ","b":"Artificial system","c":"Phylogenetic system","d":"Asexual system","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The term \"New systematics\" was introduced by:","a":"Bentham and Hooker","b":"Linnaeus","c":"Julian Huxley","d":"A.P. de Condolle","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Rattus rattus scientific name is an example of:","a":"Autonyms","b":"Tautonyms","c":"Synonyms","d":"Homonyms","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Given below is the botanical name of mango. Mark the option in which the name is correctly written.","a":"Magnifera Indica","b":"Mangifera indica","c":"Mangifera Indica","d":"Mangifera indica","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Phylogeny refers to:","a":"Natural classification","b":"Evolutionary classification","c":"Evolutionary history","d":"Origin of algae","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The basic unit of classification is:","a":"Genus","b":"Species","c":"Order","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Group of organisms that closely resemble each other and freely interbreed in nature constitute a:","a":"Species","b":"Genus","c":"Family","d":"Taxon","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"If an organism is in the same class but not in the same family but it may belong to same:","a":"Genus","b":"Species","c":"Variety","d":"Order","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The category which includes related families is:","a":"Class","b":"Phvlum","c":"Order","d":"Kingdom","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Artificial system of classification classifies plants on the basis of:","a":"One or two characters","b":"Phylogenetic trends ","c":"Many naturally existing characters","d":"None of the above","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The most important feature of all living systems is to:","a":"utilise oxygen to generate energy.","b":"replicate the genetic information.","c":"produce gametes.","d":"utilise solar energy for metabolic activities.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"NBRI is situated at:","a":"Calcutta","b":"Bombay","c":"Madras ","d":"Lucknow","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Mark the odd one in the following.","a":"Family","b":"Class","c":"Taxon","d":"Phylum","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Mark the odd one in the following.","a":"Family","b":"Class","c":"Taxon","d":"Phylum","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Who was the first to describe, that species is the unit of classification?","a":"John Ray","b":"Linnaeus","c":"Huxlev","d":"Candolle","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"An important criterion for modern day classification is:","a":"Resemblances in morphology","b":"Anatomical and physiological traits","c":"Breeding habits","d":"Presence or absence of notochord","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following taxa are not used by botanists?","a":"Kingdom & order","b":"Phylum & family","c":"Suborder & variety","d":"Phylum & sub species","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The scientific naming of plants began with publication of Linnaeus book'______’.","a":"Genera plantarum","b":"Systema naturae","c":"Species plantarum","d":"Charaka samhita","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Couplet represents the choice made between two opposite options which results in:","a":"rejection of both the option.","b":"acceptance of both the option.","c":"either acceptance or reiection of both the option.","d":"acceptance of only one and rejection of the other.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The term \"New Systematics\" was introduced by:","a":"Bentham and Hooker","b":"Linnaeus","c":"Julian Huxley","d":" A.P. de Candolle","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"A duplicate of nomenclature type is termed by a taxonomist as:","a":"Syntype","b":"Neotype","c":"Paratype","d":"Isotype","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following pair of taxa are not present in Linnaean hierarchy?","a":"Genus and variety","b":"Family and Phylum","c":"Class and species","d":"Species and variety","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The smallest unit of classification is:","a":"Family","b":"Order ","c":"Genus","d":"Species","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Morphologically similar but reproductively isolated species are called:","a":"Neontological species","b":"Sibling species","c":"Allopatric species","d":"Morpho-species","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following taxonomic category of housefly is incorrectly matched?","a":"Genus - Musca","b":"Family - Muscidae","c":"Order - Primata","d":"Class - Insecta","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following isless general incharactersas compared to genus?","a":"Species","b":"Division","c":"Class","d":"Family ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Phenetic classification is based on:","a":"sexual characteristics.","b":"the ancestral lineage of existing organisms.","c":"observable characteristics of existing organisms.","d":"dendograms based on DNA characteristics.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"\"X\" being a higher category is the assemblage of families which exhibit a few \"Y\" characters. The \"Z\" characters are less in a number as compared to different genera included in a family. Identify \"X\", \"Y\", and \"Z\".","a":"X-Order; Y - Similar; Z - Similar","b":"X-Genus; Y - Similar; Z - Different","c":"X - Species; Y - Different; Z- Similar","d":"X- Class; Y - Different; Z- Different","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Artificial system of classification was first used by:","a":"Linnaeus","b":"De Candolle","c":"Pliny the Edler","d":"Bentham and Hooker","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which one of the taxonomic aids can give comprehensive account of complete compiled information of any one genus or family at a particular time?","a":"Taxonomic key","b":"Flora","c":"Herbarium","d":"Monograph","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Classification based on sequencing of DNA and chemical nature of protein is:","a":"Chemotaxonomy ","b":" Cytotaxonomy ","c":"Adansonian taxonomy","d":"Karyotaxonomy","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following is the only taxonomic categories that has a real existence?","a":"Phylum","b":"Species ","c":"Genus","d":"Kingdom","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Who is the father of biology?","a":"Hippocrates","b":"Theophrastus","c":"Aristotle ","d":"Darwin","hint":"","correct":"c"}]